<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Wake Up Naveen</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com" />
<updated>2015-11-29T00:40:40+05:30</updated>
<id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
  <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com/</uri>
  <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nitish does it when will Naveen.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/nitish-does-it-when-will-naveen/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/nitish-does-it-when-will-naveen</id>
  <published>2015-11-26T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-11-26T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From Mayurbhanj to Malkangiri, Nabarangpur to Nayagarh and Konark to Kalahandi, people of Odisha now should have a common agenda: To check liquor menace. There are ‘war cries of Odias’ against drugs and drinks.  People of Odisha are no more unconscious about corruption, nepotism, misgovernance and opportunism. It is time to taking up social causes and raising voice for a greater cause.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Alcoholism.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Tribal Alcoholism&quot; /&gt;
   Campaign for prohibition is not new in Odisha. Freedom fighters were active during the Independence struggle to end the liquor nuisance. After the Independence, the anti-liquor movement was confined to limited pockets. 
Farmers are struggling to find labourers in Odisha. The work culture of the state has worsened drastically over the past few years. Why? People have taken to excessive drinking is shaped the state government for the problem. Until 2000, there was only one or two liquor shop for a block in the vicinity. Now, there are ten. The state government has made liquor easily accessible. Liquor shops have sprouted across the state. 
The jump was highest in rural areas. Liquor sales surged at a much faster pace. Consumption of country liquor as well as India-made foreign liquor (IMFL) increased almost 11 times. The state government changed its excise policy after Naveen Pattanik became chief minister in 2000 as the head of an alliance between Biju Janata Dal and the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP). It started allotting more liquor shops and began increasing licence fees in a bid to boost revenue. The growing importance of excise duty for Odisha, one of India’s least industrialised states, is in contrast to Haryana, a more industrialised state where liquor consumption is also high. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While growing liquor sales may have boosted the treasury, but the poor is facing disastrous situation.  A revenue model that promotes liquor sales has a huge social cost on health and status of women in a state where much of society is still feudal-minded. There are few jobs for skilled or semi-skilled youth because no big or small-scale industry has been set up due to lack of political will, bureaucratic lethargy and corruption. This has led to growing frustration among the youth, especially in rural areas, who do not wish to till land or do manual work. Many of these people connive with village administration to siphon off money from welfare schemes and blow it up on liquor. 
I am waiting for the day when Odisha government led-by drunkard Naveen Patnaik would announce 2 rupees subsidized liquor for public after 5 rupees meal. Our CM is has been overflowing with innovative ideas, and who knows the above words would be true very soon. He talks about better medical facilities in state in front of public rallies but in flipside he wants more liquor shops by e-auction.  Government starts Health Insurance under Biju Kalyan Yojana, but will it work, when the government promotes ‘Biju’ Liquor Company?  Anyway, BJD can do anything for luring votes. Everyone acquainted with this truth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of lunching a comprehensive and inclusive policy for uplifting poverty, he is doing liquor business, it always sadden me. I hope BJD and Naveen will soon realise that winning electoral battle is of minuscule importance compared to the task of making Odisha a vibrant state where equality is the creed. 
Please come join hands with party of ‘Hand,’ and show the strength of people to the Naveen and Co. who are suffering from intellectual malnutrition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written with inputs from Sanjay Kumar Bissoyi.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/nitish-does-it-when-will-naveen/&quot;&gt;Nitish does it when will Naveen.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on November 26, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding the real Amarladoo.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/found-the-real-amarladoo/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/found-the-real-amarladoo</id>
  <published>2015-11-21T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-11-21T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After days of hushed chanting that “the sky and Government betrayed” him,  Baga Paik, Nabarangpur, Odisha left behind his three sons and a loving wife, he killed himself and compelled to do so, whether Damodar Rout, a veteran ruling BJD leader believes it or not. Once Dr. Rout said: ‘Chasi Marena, Adivasi Bhika Magena’ (Neither the farmers suicide nor the tribes are beggars) but what happened in the case of Baga Paik, crushed by debt and took his life out of sheer desperation who had a loan of  56 thousand rupees for cotton farming. I protested a 12-hour sit-in fast in front of dead body to support emotionally to family where SHG members were demanding to recover loan.
Parameswar Nayak, Mayurbhanj had moderately large – 3 acres of farming field where he put his heart and hard work into farming. That’s why he couldn’t take the pain of crop failures and accumulating debt and putting his life to death. There are many such instance of farmers commit suicides in Odisha and that even at staggering rate.
Odisha farmers hardly grow cash crops but paddy farmers extortionate rates of interest charged by moneylenders is seen as one of the major reasons driving farmers to despair, while Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Maharastra farmers grow cash crops. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3oriHOtBIJOY_193726.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amar Ladoo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agriculture land with irrigation facilities in Odisha is very low compared to other States. While 98 per cent of agriculture land is irrigated in Punjab, in Odisha it is very less amount of land has irrigation facilities. Despite promising irrigation to at least 35 per cent of the cultivable land in the state since it came to power 15 years ago, the Naveen Patnaik government has failed to provide assured irrigation, not even a single acre of new land irrigated. It is still just about 14 per cent of the land is irrigated in Odisha. State Government is neglecting agriculture sector during the last 15 years. Odisha has been relegated to the position of second grade State as far as foodgrains production is concerned.
The state is facing a severe drought, the government has adopted an anti-farmer approach . The total number of farmer suicides in the state crossed the 100-mark in 2015. However, the state government is denying it. Moreover, Chief Minister didn’t take precise steps to control farmer suicides. They are dying under burden of debt. Farmers continued to commit suicide even after announcement of a drought package by the state government as it was of no use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state government had targeted to provide Rs 5,500 crore cooperative loans to farmers during Kharif, only Rs 436 crore loans were made available. Small and marginal farmers as well as share croppers were deprived of getting loans from government agencies, they were forced to take loan from money-lenders at very high rate of interest, adding crop failure and inability to repay loan were prime reasons of suicide by farmers. Farmers’ suicide had scripted a dark chapter in Odisha’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than spending afterwards on relief package to deal with farmer suicides, it will be better to take preventive measures to control this crisis. The preventive measures should be addressed on both social and economic fronts. In this connection, the importance of financial literacy, education, counselling, and medical services cannot be over-emphasised for addressing social causes. However, economic causes leading to erosion in farm income need to be taken up with a sense of urgency. Farm income is exposed to both production and market risks.Hence the real amar ladoo is in getting the farmers ready to face the ruthlessness of a globalized market where everyother country is heavily subsidizing its agriculture to ensure food security, else hapless farmers will keep on dying and people like me will be protesting on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written with inputs from Sanjay Kumar Bissoyi.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/found-the-real-amarladoo/&quot;&gt;Finding the real Amarladoo.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on November 21, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Letter to Modi from a Human]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/an-open-letter-to-modi/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/an-open-letter-to-modi</id>
  <published>2015-11-17T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-11-17T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Prime Minister Modi,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I extend my congratulations to you on your appointment to me as migrant-city-labour from native-place-based happy labour. I had a great expectation from you. Today, my disappointment forced to write a letter to you. I am an ordinary citizen of the country. After seven year of happy life, now, I am bound migrate from my village in order to search for livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congress government’s rural safety program MGNREGA, where we worked with much enthusiasm comes to an end, because you reduced allocation for this scheme, and also there is no alternate of it. It was life line for poor like us. Though it has not removed our poverty, but it helps to fill the hungry stomachs. You run miles in the morning for losing fat from body, at the same time we also run miles in the morning in the search of food for two times. The drought like situation in the state brings turbulent economic condition. The worrisome at large. You gave a deadly blow to our income and purchasing power. Although there are serious loop holes like huge delays in wage payments, poor quality of accessing work, but nothing is better than something. Instead of transformational changes in the scheme, you are silently trying abolish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While whole India celebrated Diwali, my family members’ tears are falling continuously since I left home, though they attempted to hide fill up eyes to me, but I can experience it. You have been travelling to abroad since you became Prime Minister, I don’t know what I will get from it, but for me, there is God, where food is. So I decided to migrate in the search of food. I don’t know what is my future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally sir , I want to say something. You have said that Hindus and Muslims must decide what they want to fight, each other or poverty. To me this is nothing but another empty slogan because poverty is inextricably connected to religion, caste and class. For vote you politicians can do anything. Unless we face up to these challenges with greater honesty and courage, not just our poverty but our backwardness will remain indeed incurable. But it will not going to happen because enslavement is our religion.  Nothing… poor men have nothing… rich men need nothing…nothing is more evil than the devil… and nothing is greater than God… but if you eat nothing, you’ll die (eventually)… I am not frustrated; hope one day better days will come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With kind regards,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indian (Not a Hindu, Muslim or etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Author: Sanjay Kumar Bisoyi,He blogs at (https://thetribalissue.wordpress.com) .&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/an-open-letter-to-modi/&quot;&gt;Open Letter to Modi from a Human&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on November 17, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Neutrality that needs us to take sides.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/neutrality-that-needs-sides-taken/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/neutrality-that-needs-sides-taken</id>
  <published>2015-04-16T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-04-16T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I am writing this post two of the largest ISP (Internet Service Providers) in US, Times Warner and Comcast are seeking possibilities to become one company. That means one company will have control on about 80% of the internet access in USA. Citizens over there are terrified at this proposition because inspite of all the federal controls against monopoly that exist in USA customers fear the two players getting together can result in price fixation and hence internet will become inaccessible for some customers. I am bringing this up to open our minds the real reason why not just the netizens but all of India who have access to internet and who do not should stand up against Modi sarkar’s attempt to give us a non neutral net. 
   Now what the fuss is this net neutrality? In simple terms it means democracy of internet. Like in a democracy every citizen has equal rights irrespective of caste, creed and religion every person on the internet should have the freedom to access every website he/she wants to access with equal ease. Most of the ISPs or specifically mobile internet providers in India have approached TRAI the regulating authority to allow them to basically take away this democracy from the internet. The reason they claim is protecting their revenues and hence their investment that they have made in the telecom infrastructure, but in reality all that they want is to be rewarded for not innovating. Traditionally telecoms make about 33% of their revenue from services other than calls and a big share of this is by the revenues they earn from their SMS, MMS and other VAS packages. The companies have to spend very little in providing these services and hence all the revenue they make goes to serve their bottomline. But with the proliferation of smart phones and the 3G internet, services like Whatsapp and Skype(internet telephone) are becoming popular. These services are directly competing with those provided by the telecom providers and come for free through innovative business models. And these services have achieved billion dollar valuations. So the telecom companies have a double greed working here, first they want to block services which are in direct competition of the services they provide and second they want to have a share of profitability that these internet companies are generating. Its very similar to a situation where you decided to drive a taxi during the Nabkalebar, you bought your taxi paid the road tax got the license and started operating. You were good at taxi driving so soon you got good business and not the RTO feels you should pay more taxes because your are profitable by driving on the transport department roads. 
      Net neutrality though may seem like a not so important issue, if the internet was not neutral almost all of us will be affected, in many ways now and even more ways in the future. Leave aside access to over the top services like Whatsapp, if you are someone like me you are probably getting a lot of your news not from TV or newspaper but from the internet, if your service provider has access to control what to show you what not you will only get what the service providers give you. For example I am a regular reader of gfiles website, if there is a controversial report on some issue and my service providers decides not to show me the post or charge me extra for the post, won’t my views about the issue be shaped by what my service provider decides to show me? 
   Apart from access to our favorite websites, lack of net neutrality will be a roadblock in getting net access to the part of population which are still unconnected. Because the service providers will get freedom to decide a low quality internet which is not the quality internet for the group of customers who are not lucrative for the company. Example are the low priced student call plans from various service providers which costs very less but you can just call your parents. Imagine having a internet which gives access to a useless job site called BabaJobs when everybody knows that naukri.com is the largest job search portal of India.
   Think about it and if you believe this neutrality needs us to take sides, please call up your MP to bring up this net neutrality in Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/neutrality-that-needs-sides-taken/&quot;&gt;Neutrality that needs us to take sides.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on April 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Jumla in Making.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/a-jumla-in-making/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/a-jumla-in-making</id>
  <published>2015-03-22T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-03-22T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not just once or twice, atleast in 9 public meetings in the last two months Shri Narendra Modi has beaten is 56inch hollow chest for being able to collect more than 2 lakh crore rupees in revenue for the state though the coal auctions apart from that he has also made tall claims about his achievement in being able to conduct auctions for coal blocks. Its very clear from the stand of BJP CMs in Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh before and after elections that auctions were not the preferred way to allocate coal blocks in BJPs think tank. MMS during UPA-2 regime tried to push through auctions for coal blocks but had faced heavy resistance from CMs of 4 states MP,Chhatisgarh, Odisha &amp;amp; WB. Two of these states were ruled by BJP, one by Naveen Patnaik ex partner in business of BJP &amp;amp; the fourth then was a ruled by the communists. There existed no political will in the nation to enforce auctioning of coal blocks which I believe has 2 sides some positive and some negative. The noise about the auctions may be emanating from the 56 inch hollow chest but in reality the auctions were enforced on the government by the Supreme Court. So if anyone is to be given credit for the auctions it should be our fair and strong Judiciary and not us the political class be it of any party. Some of us did not understand the business of coal and out of the few who understood that ones canvassing for auctions were the minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claimed 2 lakh crore rupees that Modi sarkar just earned for us is all but paper money that will not reach the public and if it will by the time it reaches there are chances that rupee would have depreciated atleast by about 20%. Because the coal block are being leased out for a time period of 30years or the life of the coal mine whichever is lower. And more than 60% of the coal blocks that are being auctioned have not been developed yet, so until they are developed and starts producing irrespective of the auction value the lessee does not have to pay a single penny to the government. Its like I buy a calf from you by paying Rs 1000 but until the calf becomes a cow and starts producing milk, I do not pay you anything. But you have given a Rs 200 party celebrating earning Rs 1000 from selling the calf. For a similar crime the Rajas of Satyam are being held and may be behind bars for a very long time. Taking some specifics Modi sarkar has claimed that Odisha will earn Rs 6000 crore from the current auctions apart from the royalty rev share which the state was gaining irrespective of auctions or not. Now in the Rs 6000 crore there are about 17 licenses on allocation to coal fields which are yet to produce a single kilo of coal. And there is no timeline to when will these mines be developed by the lessee and coal will be produced. So any 7 year old kid can tell you that the numbers Modi sarkar is throwing do not add up. And I think there is understanding within the BJP cadres too that the numbers do not add up but since Jumlas are essential part of BJPs existence the cadres are just sucking it in giving their brains a good rest. I am no fortune teller but just by virtue of some understanding of financial numbers I can safely predict that 2 lakh crores from coal is going to be the new #jumla of BJP’s prime minister Shri Narendra Modi.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/a-jumla-in-making/&quot;&gt;A Jumla in Making.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on March 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Indispensable Prince & His Coterie.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/the-indispensable-prince-and-his-coterie/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/the-indispensable-prince-and-his-coterie</id>
  <published>2015-01-28T00:24:48+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-01-28T00:24:48+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When media got a glimpse of Shri Arun Patnaik, grandson of Shri Biju Patnaik in an event at Cuttack, they made the most of the few seconds of footage that they could get by running the images in cycle on almost all local channels. It was almost like seeing a Vine gif of him saying “Not at the moment.”. Though I didn’t hear the question he was asked but I was told he was being asked if he is about to play a role in the business of BJD. Yes business here does not mean their real business of minerals and chit fund, but their side business that is politics. His short four word response may have been naive or may have been a very calculated move by the strategic coterie of Naveen Patnaik. But whatever that was, it was enough to get hours of footage attending to him and several square inches of newsprint took up the issue the next morning. The last time we had heard of him was during the general election 2014 when there was a word that Arun Patnaik is going to replace Shri Baijayant Panda as BJD’s candidate for Kendrapada parliamentary constituency. Which was not to happen subsequently.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/images/arun.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  There was no specific opinion about Arun Patnaik’s  innings in BJD from the press fraternity it had the whole variety of guesses and speculations some saying he is supposed to enter in 2 years from now to not entering at all. I don’t know what is Naveen Patnaik’s plan with respect to Arun Patnaik’s entry to BJD. But there are three things which are very clear and I am  sure will happen. First whenever he joins BJD he will be the supremo of the party a.l.a Naveen Patna, second he is going to be the BJD’s chief minister candidate in 2019 assembly elections which BJD will fight in alliance with BJP in Odisha and third Shri Baijayant Panda and Shri Pinaki Mishra will be the kingmakers inside BJD after 2019 elections. The first and second prediction are easy and inline with the popular view.  Now let me explain why the third is ought to happen. 
By the time we face 2019 elections Naveen Patnaik would have lost his marketable image tainted by Chit Fund, Mining, Discretionary Quota and Coal Scam. Along with that young voters get impatient over his inaction and mis directed policies especially related to employment generation. In the past growing unemployment has helped Naveen Patnaik in his pursuit of power basically due to the financial largesse that he has been providing laser targeted to people who have shown allegiance to the green conch. But psychologists have proved it that people get used to things after the nouveau excitement wanes off. Free rice , free house, a contract to do 10meters of village road will not have the magnetism that they are having now. They would search for substance in the programs. When someone rules for 20 years less and less people will compare their life 20 yrs ago to the day, but rather compare the nett delta in the quality of life improvement in last 5 years. Naveen Patnaik has never has had to do any real policy decisions in trying times and neither does he have any ministerial colleague who does have that experience , hence with revenues drying from mining and other sectors due to nett loss of trust in the Naveen regime affecting business environment in Odisha with the needle not moving on large projects like POSCO and PCPL SEZ. In the next 4 years Naveen Patnaik will present budgets which will be mile wide and inch deep, it may work as a placebo to people of Odisha for a year or so but eventually is gonna come back and burst in Naveen Patnaik’s face. When you have some substance then you add a lot of propaganda it may work, but no substance and just propaganda won’t work. So bottomline come 2019 Naveen Patnaik will be at the bottom of his popularity, so much so that it may be hard for him to conduct public meetings in western and southern odisha. 
What will Naveen Patnaik do when he is faced with anti-incumbency, loss of popularity and some loss of health also, he needs a face that is somewhat presentable and hope pulls some crowd. Simple in comes the scion who would see the same dreams as his grandfather who he probably never met. Arun Patnaik will be the face of BJD and go to the polls. With that change, there will be a change in a coterie and three people with long term vision to wrest power will be the new coterie. The ghee extracting huge minister will suddenly seem like a smartass PhD in politics when his prediction comes true and he conveniently shifts his licks from one a$$ to another. And the real deal will come to Shri Baijayant Panda and Shri Pinaki Mishra who are often seen as adversaries inside BJD. While the so called leaders (read servants) of Naveen Patnaik  are fighting the fire here in the state for a expiring comatose leader in Naveen Patnaik, while smart and far sighted Mr Panda and Mr Mishra are getting close to the future of Biju Legacy (ignoring his role in India’s defeat in 1962 Sino-Indian war by selling of german winter gear in sarojini nagar market which was meant to be dropped for Indian Army soldiers on China front) in New Delhi. 
  Arun Patnaik will not only change the pith of BJD. But will pose a formidable challenge for us as a opposition in comparison to a tainted scamster that is Naveen Patnaik. BJD saving Arun Patnaik  till 2019 elections may prove to be a master stroke because no data is always better than bad data. Having no information about him, his ideas and ideologies we will be left with no groove to run a campaign against him, and hence will have to fall back to pick on personality trivialities which we have been trying since long with Naveen Patnaik and dont have a good record to show. So, its about time we take good notice of this Biju scion as our opponent and study him to act when he is here. From the little i could dig up from Linkedin about him. He seems to be a arts graduate from Wesleyan University in Connecticut, United States. Is the CEO of a firm called AquaAgri Processing Private Limited and is director of five companies along with his dad Prem Patnaik viz. HHS INDIA PRIVATE LIMITED, CANTON SPICE COMPANY PRIVATE LIMITED, HARYANA COATED PAPERS LIMITED, JAMUNA ENTERPRISES PVT LTD &amp;amp;  HEALTH AND HOME SHOPPING INDIA Private Limited. This is not sufficient the more we know the better.       &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/the-indispensable-prince-and-his-coterie/&quot;&gt;The Indispensable Prince & His Coterie.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on January 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take My Land, Take My Hand.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/take-my-land-take-my-hand/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/take-my-land-take-my-hand</id>
  <published>2015-01-26T02:28:37+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-01-26T02:28:37+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;47000 candidates registered online to participate in a recruitment drive conducted by Naveen Sarkar where they promised to rope in 300 companies to come and hire from the pool. Breaking News, nothing of that sort happened or is there to happen in government’s plans. Employment, Technical Education and Training (ETET) Department headed by a stooge of Naveen who till recent was busy covering up his sorry a$$ in some phony building violation deal and pushing a chit funded SUV under his rug, has already postponed the drive twice, the recent one was in November. And you have to give credit to his shamelessness when he said the drive was being postponed due to lack of interest from recruiters which must have been the pre requisite to moot such a campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I won’t be doing justice if I blame this botch tormenting the technical grads of our state square on him, because we all know where lies the control to all these policy decisions of government. Its that famous third floor, which I believe was a puzzle given to us by the great Harekrushna Mahatab who had some premonitions that a third grade person is gonna occupy it for the longest amount of time. Naveen Patnaik probably never ever had to do a job and hence does not understand what loosing a year out of job means to a young, energetic &amp;amp; educated gentleman or woman. His callouss policy making totally counter to the future and interest of youth in our state has got us to a point that the employment generation in our state is negative now. There are numerous industrial estates around the state where small &amp;amp; medium industrial units flourished a decade ago will now remind you of a set of a haunted movie. You don’t have to go too far to find just look in the industrial estates surrounding Bhubaneswar, you will get the idea. But you would wonder where did those gazillions of US dollars in investment go you would ask. Apparently they have gone to mysterious crevices of the all consuming black hole called Naveen Sarkar. Who has converted trading our soil, water, sea and land for virtual dollars into a well rehearsed routine. Tata Steel who is the anchor tenant of the industrial park being developed on 3500 acres at Gopalpur, got about 1000 acres of land from the government. One would guess government has given the land as a measure towards employment generation. But that wishful thinking will blow in your face when you know Tata Steel who has secured more iron ores than any other private steel company in Odisha has employed only 64 Odias in its under construction steel facility at Kalinganagar Industrial Complex, Jajpur. Simillar is the story with POSCO India Private Limited who till date has employed only 8 Odias. Naveen Sarkar has signed MoUs with 49 steel plants and all these 49 units have managed to absorb is a mere 19,300 persons, across all operations. Compare that to the 47000 technical graduates only who have registered for the mirage that is ETET recruitment drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is no anomaly Naveen Sarkar has never been sensitive to the most pressing issue of our state that is unemployment. Most pressing because unemployment is the root cause of a lot of other problems like alcoholism, growing violence , maoism, etc we face in our state. 10,42,826 educated youth have registered themselves in employment exchanges across the state an astronomical number compared to 42,222 who have been recruited by different organizations in last 14 years of Naveen’s rule. Naveen’s comatose and has no empathy for the youth of Odisha, so it is unto us if we choose to suck it up to his toxic policies on employment generation or force him to get his act together and give us a future.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/take-my-land-take-my-hand/&quot;&gt;Take My Land, Take My Hand.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on January 26, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annihilated Our Present, Screwed Our Future.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://wakeupnaveen.com/annihilated-our-present-screwed-our-future/" />
  <id>http://wakeupnaveen.com/annihilated-our-present-screwed-our-future</id>
  <published>2015-01-13T03:40:27+05:30</published>
  <updated>2015-01-13T03:40:27+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pradeep Majhi</name>
    <uri>http://wakeupnaveen.com</uri>
    <email>iycpradeep@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are crimes and then there are sins, what Naveen Sarkar is doing to our state is gold standard of both of these. Having been pulled of one of the largest heists of 20,000 crore from gullible middle class population of Odisha, it is on a crusade to destroy our future by sucking the soul and purpose out of our primary education system. Isn’t it amusing that Mr Patnaik promises to get rid of all kuchha houses from the state when in the last 14 years of his rule 30% of our schools don’t have required number of classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary education encompasses a vision of education that empower rural Odisha by creating a sustainable future. By promoting primary education we build a foundation for secondary and tertiary education. Majority of primary education providers in rural Odisha are government run schools. But why rural Odisha’s primary education is shocking according to recent research published by ASER? By improving literacy and numeracy during primary education we provide more knowledgeable and productive labor force. According to World Bank studies, this also has a direct and positive impact on future earnings and farmer productivity, and also it bestows significant health and poverty alleviation benefits (IEG, 2006). In a cross-sectional study of 50 developing countries, Gupta et al. (2002) found a positive corelation between increased public spending with educational attainment and health status.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students leave schools they should have understanding and knowledge to contribute for a sustainable future but an AESR 2013 report said even though number of private schools have gone up in rural Odisha the overall literacy and numeracy rates in kids have been remarkable lower compared to previous years. I think myself why parents prefer private schools? I studied in a remote school where we never had any private school and I think we had best teachers considering I did my schooling in late 80s. I know many of my schoolmates have gone to premier institutes in India and abroad after schooling from rural primary school. I ask myself why 15.9 % of Std 3 kids can’t even read a letter in Odisha? Similarly 15.4 % of Std 3 kids can’t even recognise numbers 1-9 (AESR 2012). Shockingly according to the same report number of students in Std 3 who were able to do substractions were reduced approximately by 50% in just 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naveen Sarkar is unable to improve the learning skills of half its primary school children, in the last four years and today it has fallen to alarming lows. Similar deterioration in quality of education is also noted among other standards student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent studies have also reported the increase in number of private schools in rural areas and increasing number of parents are willing to send their kids to private school rather than government run schools. When I asked this question to myself I realized the answer is easy, every parents want their kids to get quality education and do best in future. But can all parents afford private school’s tuition fees? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I visited my school in rural Odisha and I noticed there is no improvement in infrastructure. It’s exactly in the same boat as it was 25 years ago. There are even reduced number of classrooms and the building looks old and unsafe for children. AESR had similar findings where they found nearly 22% of schools in Odisha don’t have drinking water facility. In 2012 less than half (49%) of schools in Odisha had toilet facilities for kids (AESR 2012). I think we should concentrate on these basic amenities first when we speak of “swachha bharat abhiyan”.  India is not considered a poor nation anymore but it surprises me when basic amenities like drinking water is not available in schools of Odisha. I was privileged to meet some of my school teachers, most of them are retired now, I was told school is not the same it was before. Number of staff have been reduced and also the number of student has gone down as most parents preferring for private schools.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.manjul.com/cartoons/wp-content/uploads/2008/10/051008pol.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under its Right to Education (RTE) Act, passed in 2009, a free and compulsory education is guaranteed for all children aged between six and fourteen, and recent figures for primary school enrollment stand impressive but going to school is one thing and the quality of the education you get is another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried to find an answer I found several reasons which according to my view possibly contribute to this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lack of enough funding: 
Despite the need for increases in education spending, as a state, Odisha remains a low level spender on education. Recent budget figures show that in terms of expenditure on primary to tertiary education, Odisha sits at lowest level among all other states.An AESR 2013 report finds more than 50% of school kids (aged 5-14) have arrangements for private tuition in Odisha compared to 10-15% in other states like Maharashtra, Karnataka and Gujrat. This shows lack of trust by parents in present primary schools run by Odisha government.In 2014 budget there is a gross provision of 9352 Cr INR for schools and mass education. Comparing other developed states it’s significantly lower proportion of expenditure. Considering Odisha’s present condition of schools government definitely needs to spend lot more than this to catch up with developed states. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allocation of funds and their management:
The proper allocation and management of this fund is also very important. Some of the smaller states like Mizoram are doing lot better than Odisha in primary education with significantly lower expenditure. There are plenty of loopholes in present system of education where revenue is spent in a way where growth of schools and primary education in rural Odisha is difficult.Odisha under Naveen Patnaik is filled with contradictions in almost everything you see. Education of course is no different story. The budget allocation to education has dropped year after year. 80% of teachers in the schools are temporary teachers who are indeed eligible for permanent posting but government in spite of their claims of some mega surplus budget is not able to make them regular or appoint sufficient teachers for our children. Creating unemployment bloat in the present and at the same time planting the seeds to give use a whole majority of unemployable youth in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say Nero fiddled while Rome burned.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com/annihilated-our-present-screwed-our-future/&quot;&gt;Annihilated Our Present, Screwed Our Future.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Pradeep Majhi at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wakeupnaveen.com&quot;&gt;Wake Up Naveen&lt;/a&gt; on January 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
